Guide to the Friends of Democracy Records, 1937-1950 and undated RL.11263
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Friends of Democracy records
1937-1950 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Friends of Democracy (U.S.)
Human Rights Archive (Duke University)
RL.11263
2 Linear Feet 2 boxes
Collection of research files and materials kept by the Friends of Democracy while they monitored various fascist and communist propaganda organizations and figures during World War II and immediately following the war.
Biographical / Historical
The Friends of Democracy organization was founded by Unitarian minister Leon Milton Birkhead in 1937. The group described itself as "a non-partisan, non-sectarian, non-profit, anti-totalitarian propaganda agency." In 1939 their offices were moved to New York City, an early branch of the group. John Dewey, Thomas Mann, Van Wyck Brooks, and Will Durant were all prominent members.
A biography of L.M. Birkhead can be found here, courtesy of the Unitarian Universalist History & Heritage Society: http://uudb.org/articles/leonmiltonbirkhead.html
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Friends of Democracy Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a transfer from Perkins Library in 2012.
Collection Overview
Collection includes meeting notes, radio transcripts, speech transcripts, and reports created by Friends of Democracy as it monitored various fascist- and communist-sympathizers, as well as materials, literature, newsletters, and correspondence collected by Friends of Democracy documenting the various activities, writings, and beliefs of those groups. Files are arranged alphabetically by name of the monitored group or person. Groups represented include American Nazi groups, anti-semitic propagandists, pro-Soviet or pro-Communist organizations, anti-Roosevelt organizations, isolationist groups or leaders, and other figures that the Friends of Democracy deemed threatening to American democracy or world peace. Figures monitored include Charles Lindbergh, Hamilton Fish, Elizabeth Dillings, Upton Close, William J. Grace, Gerald Winrod, and others.
World War, 1939-1945; Propaganda, German; Propaganda, Anti-German; Propaganda, Anti-communist; Anti-communist movements -- United States; Radio broadcasting -- 1940-1950; Friends of Democracy (U.S.); Birkhead, L.M. (Leon Milton), 1885-1954; Lindbergh, Charles A. (Charles Augustus), 1902-1974; Fish, Hamilton, 1888-1991; Winrod, Gerald B (Gerald Burton); German American Bund; America First Committee; Human Rights Archive (Duke University); Smith, Gerald L. K. (Gerald Lyman Kenneth), 1898-1976
- Internal literature
  Scope and Contents
  Materials, largely drafts and notes, relating to Friends of Democracy's own publications and projects.
  - A Confidential Statement Concerning Pro-Nazi and Anti-Semitic Organizations, 1930s (Box 1)
    Drafts, proofs, and typescripts of pamphlet issued by L.M. Birkhead and FOD
  - Congressional Project, 1942-1943 (Box 1)
    Miscellaneous notes and drafts from an untitled FOD project opposing various Congressional candidates (incl. Hamilton Fish)
- Name or Organizational Files, 1938-1950 and undated
  Files created and kept by members of the Friends of Democracy as they monitored and documented activities of various people and organizations throughout the United States. Formats included in these files include FOD's own internal notes about various meetings they attended or people they met; literature, mass mailings, subscription letters, and circulars created by the organizations FOD monitored; press releases written by FOD denouncing a particular group or public figure; clippings and literature mentioning a group or figure; and other miscellaneous materials documenting a group or person's writings, radio broadcasts, appearances, or beliefs.
  - America First Committee, 1941-1942 (Box 1)
    FOD notes, copies of correspondence
  - Anglo-Saxon Federation of America, 1946-1947 (Box 1)
    Convention program, mass mailings
  - The Bill Smiths: The Average Citizens Group (Hattiesburg, MI), 1946 (Box 2)
    Newsletter
  - Bricker, John (Chicago), 1944-1945 (Box 1)
    FOD notes about his speeches, meetings
  - Brocks, Wayland, undated (Box 1)
    FOD notes
  - Busbey, Fred E., 1945-1946 (Box 1)
    FOD notes re: speeches, meetings
  - Catholic Mothers and Daughters of America, Inc., 1946 (Box 1)
  - Christian Business Men's Committee of Chicago, 1945 (Box 1)
  - Citizens USA Committee, 1943-1945 (Box 1)
    FOD notes re: committee meetings, transcriptions of circulars
  - Close, Upton (Los Angeles), 1941-1948 (Box 1)
    Mass mailings, radio broadcast transcripts, clippings, FOD notes
  - Committee for American Independence, 1945-1946 (Box 1)
    FOD notes re: meetings
  - Committee for Constitutional Government, 1945-1950 (Box 1)
    Circulars, reports, literature
  - Constitutional Americans (Chicago), 1943-1946 (Box 1)
    FOD notes, mass mailing
  - Constitutional Educational League, 1941-1948 (Box 1)
    FOD notes re: Joe Kamp and the CEL
  - Constitutional Money League of America/National Constitutional Party (Minden, Nebraska), 1943-1948 (Box 1)
    Newsletters, flyers, and pamphlets
  - Council Against Intolerance in America (New York City), 1943-1949 (Box 1)
    Stamps, press releases, flyers
  - Council for Democracy, 1944-1945 (Box 1)
    Mass mailings
  - Day, Stephen, 1944-1946 (Box 1)
    FOD notes, radio broadcast transcripts
  - Democratic Tract Society (Oklahoma), 1948 (Box 2)
    Anti-Dewey leaflet
  - Fish, Hamilton (New York), 1945-1947 (Box 1)
    FOD anti-Fish campaign materials, promotional literature, mass mailings
  - Fleck, John J. (Philadelphia), 1940-1946 (Box 1)
    FOD notes, writings by Fleck
  - Foundation of Catholics for Human Brotherhood, 1940-1941 (Box 1)
    Mass mailings, literature
  - German American Bund, 1937-1940 (Box 1)
    Printed materials, flyers
  - Grace, William J., 1946 (Box 1)
    Materials re: Grace's connections with Citizens Keep America Out of War and the Citizens USA Committee. FOD notes, radio broadcast transcripts.
  - Holt, Rush D. (West Virginia), 1940-1941 (Box 1)
    FOD notes, speech transcripts
  - Independent Citizens' Committee of the Arts, Sciences, and Professions, 1945-1946 (Box 1)
    Newsletters, postcards, flyers
  - Keep America Out of War Congress (New York City), 1940 (Box 1)
    Flyers, postcards, button
  - Kent, Tyler, 1941-1946 (Box 1)
    Printed materials, mass mailings
  - Kister, Frederick, undated (Box 2)
    Broadside for Christian Veterans of America: Workers of the World Unite, Destroy Communism
  - Kullgren, William, 1942 (Box 2)
    Newsletter by Kullgren.
  - Lincoln, James Finney (Cleveland), 1943-1945 and undated (Box 1)
    Includes handbooks and other materials documenting the wage, labor, and salary bonus policies of the Lincoln Electric Company
  - Lindbergh, Charles A., 1941 (Box 1)
    FOD notes and press releases denouncing Lindbergh; publications by Lindbergh, flyers
  - Lovell, J.A., 1944-1947 (Box 1)
    Materials relating to Kingdom's Digest publication. Postcards, mass mailings, circulars
  - Lutheran Research Society (Detroit), 1946-1949 (Box 1)
    Mass mailings, newsletters
  - McCormick, Robert R. (Chicago), 1943-1944 (Box 1)
    Anti-Chicago Tribune resolutions, other writings
  - Mertig, Kurt (New York City), 1945-1947 (Box 1)
    FOD notes re: Mertig and Citizen's Protective League
  - National Blue Star Mothers of America, 1946 (Box 2)
    Letter to Truman objecting to the recognition of Israel
  - National Council of American-Soviet Friendship, 1945-1947 (Box 1)
    Circulars, flyers
  - National Council of the Arts, Sciences, and Professions, 1949 (Box 1)
    Materials re: Cultural and Scientific Conference for World Peace, invitations, correspondence
  - National Physicians Committee (Chicago), 1944-1946 (Box 1)
  - Patriotic Research Bureau (Chicago), 1941-1948 and undated (Box 1)
    FOD notes on PRB and Elizabeth Dillings, newsletters, circulars
  - Peace Now Movement, 1942-1943 (Box 1)
    Circulars
  - Permanent Fair Employment Practice Committee, 1944-1946 (Box 1)
    Mass mailings, pamphlets re: FEPC
  - Serbian National Defense Council of America, 1944 (Box 1)
  - Smith, Gerald L.K. (St. Louis, MO; Detroit, MI; and Los Angeles, CA), 1944-1949; 9 folders (Box 2)
    FOD notes and drafts denouncing Smith, as well as collected mass mailings, flyers, broadsides, and newsletters written by Gerald L.K. Smith on behalf of several organizations, including the Christian Nationalist Crusade, the America First Party Crusade, the Democratic Tract Society, and the Nationalist News Service. Includes assorted issues from Smith's newsletter The Cross and the Flag.
  - Southard, Earl (Chicago), 1945-1947 (Box 1)
    Mass mailings, solicitations, literature re: Citizens Press
  - Southern Conference for Human Welfare, 1945-1946 (Box 1)
    Pamphlets, mass mailings
  - Springer, Harvey (Englewood, Colorado), 1947-1950; 2 folders (Box 1, Box 2)
    Newsletters, solitications
  - Steele, Walter S., 1940-1947 (Box 1)
    Materials re: Steele, National Republic, and National Republican organizations. Includes FOD notes and press releases, circulars, and publications by Steele
  - Tool Owners Union, 1946 (Box 1)
  - We, the Mothers, Mobilize for America, Inc., 1942-1946 (Box 1)
    FOD notes, flyers, pamphlets
  - Winrod, Gerald (Wichita, Kansas), 1946-1949; 2 folders (Box 1, Box 2)
    Newsletters, mass mailings re: Defenders of the Christian Faith